[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]
So far in this specialization data has always looked pretty beautiful.
حتى الآن في هذا التخصص، ظهرت البيانات دائمًا بشكل منسق جدًا .
We sometimes end the look at little features in the area like taking raw text
أحيانًا ننتهي من النظر إلى الميزات الصغيرة في المنطقة مثل أخذ النص الأولي
and turning into counts of words, the TFIDF, sometimes we created
والتحول إلى عدد الكلمات، TFIDF، وفي بعض الأحيان أنشأنا مزايا أكثر تقدما
more advanced feature like polynomials, sines and cosines and so on.
مثل كثيرات الحدود، sines و cosines وما إلى ذلك.
We did feature transformations,
لقد قمنا بعمل تحويلات،
feature engineering but we always observe all of our data, so
هندسة المزايا ولكن نحن دائمًا نلاحظ جميع البيانات لدينا،
for every feature we always observe every possible value for every data point.
لكل ميزة، نلاحظ دائمًا كل قيمة ممكنة لكل نقطة بيانات.
Now that, is rarely true in the real world.
من الناحية الواقعية، نادرًا ما يحدث ذلك.
Real world data tends to be pretty messy, and
تميل البيانات في العالم الواقعي إلى الفوضى
often is fraught with missing data, and unobserved values.
وفي كثير من الأحيان تفتقد للمدخلات، وتعج بالقيم التي تفتقد للمراجعة.
And this is a significant issue we should always be on the lookout for.
وهذه قضية مهمة يجب الحذر منها دائمًا.
In today's module, we're going to talk about some of the basic concepts and ideas
في الوحدة الحالية، سنتحدث عن بعض المفاهيم والأفكار الأساسية
of what you can do to try to address, missing data in a learning problem.
حول ما يمكنك القيام به لمحاولة معالجة البيانات المفقودة ومشكلة التعلم.
Approaches to dealing with missing data are better understood in the context of
تعتبر طرق التعامل مع البيانات المفقودة مفهومة بشكل أفضل في سياق
a particular learning algorithm.
خوارزميات التعلم المحددة.
So for this module, we're going to pick decision trees as a way to kind of better
في هذه الوحدة، سنقوم باختيار طريقة التسلسل في اتخاذ القرارات لنلاحظ بشكل أفضل أثر البيانات المفقودة،
see the impact of missing data, and some of the key approaches to dealing with it.
بالإضافة إلى بعض الطرق الرئيسية للتعامل معها.
Again, we're going to be dealing with loan data.
مرة أخرى، سوف نتعامل مع بيانات القروض.
So as input xi is coming out, another term of the loan, your credit history, and so
إذا ظهر الإدخال xi، كمصطلح خاص بالقروض، أو تاريخ الائتمان الخاص بك، وما إلى ذلك،
on, we're going to push it through this crazy decision tree,
سنقوم بدفعه في هذا التسلسل المعقد لاتخاذ القرارات،
set to make a decision, whether your loan is safe, or your loan is risky.
فهو مهيأ لاتخاذ القرارات، لتحديد ما إذا كان القرض آمنًا، أم محفوفًا بالمخاطر.
Which is going to be the output y hat i, that we're trying to decide here.
والذي سيكون الناتج y i، الذي نحاول أن نقرر بشأنه.
As we discussed thus far, we've assumed that all the data was fully observed.
كما ناقشنا حتى الآن، افترضنا أن جميع البيانات قد تم الاطلاع عليها بالكامل.
So nothing was missing.
وبالتالي لم يكن هناك شيء مفقود.
So for every row of the data, for every feature we observed, for
لكل صف من صفوف البيانات، ولكل ميزة تم الاطلاع عليها،
example the credit was excellent, fair, or poor.
مثل افتراض أن الائتمان إما ممتاز أو متوسط أو رديء.
If the term of the loan was three years or five years, if the income was high or low.
وإذا كانت مدة القرض ثلاث سنوات أو خمس سنوات، وإذا كان الدخل مرتفعًا أو منخفضًا.
And we will observe the output of course, say for risky.
وسوف نلاحظ النتيجة بالطبع، ولنفترض أنها مخاطرة.
Now, in reality you may have missing data.
في العالم الواقعي قد تتعامل مع بيانات مفقودة.
So missing data, for example in this highlighted row might say I know that for
إذن فالبيانات المفقودة، على سبيل المثال في هذا الصف المظلل قد توضح المعنى وراء أخذ هذا القرض،
this particular loan application the credit was poor, the income was high.
فالائتمان ضعيف، والدخل مرتفع.
Turned out to be a risky loan, but
كما يتبين أنه قرض محفوف بالمخاطر،
nobody entered in there, whether the loan was a three year loan or five year loan.
ولكن لا يوجد هنا أي مدخلات عما إذا كان القرض لمدة ثلاث سنوات أو خمس سنوات.
And that may be true for multiple data points.
وقد يكون الحال كذلك في نقاط متعددة من البيانات.
And the question is, what can we do about this?
والسؤال هو، ماذا يمكننا أن نفعل حيال ذلك؟
What impact is on our learning algorithm, what happens?
وما وقع التأثير على خوارزمية التعلم الخاصة بنا؟
Well missing data can impact a learning algorithm both in the training phase,
يمكن للبيانات المفقودة أن تؤثر على خوارزمية التعلم في مرحلة التدريب،
because I don't know how to train a model when you have this
لأنني لا أعرف كيف أقوم بتدريب نموذج
question marks we know what values those are.
في حالة وجود علامات استفهام، فتلك القيم غامضة.
And it can have an impact on prediction time.
ويمكن أن يكون لها تأثير عند وقت التنبؤ الفعلي.
Let's say I build a great decision tree, I put it out in the wild.
لنفترض أنني أنشأت تسلسلًا كبيرًا لاتخاذ القرارات، لأقوم بعد ذلك بعرضها.
Banks. Somebody an application in there but
على البنوك أو الأشخاص أو التطبيقات
we don't know a particular entry.
لنكتشف بعد ذلك افتقاد مدخل محدد.
What predictions do we make?
إذن، فما التوقعات الناتجة؟
So, let's be more specific, let's say that we have this tree that I learned from data
دعونا نكون أكثر تحديدًا، لنفترض أننا لدينا هذا التسلسل المستنبط من البيانات
and I have particular input where the credit was poor, the term was five years
وكان لدي مدخلات خاصة حيث الائتمان ضعيف، والمدة خمس سنوات
but the income was a question mark, I don't know the income of this person.
ولكن الدخل مجهول، لا أعرف دخل هذا الشخص.
So, I tried to go down the decision tree, I hit credit first, credit was poor.
لذلك من خلال تسلسل القرارات، اطلعت على قيمة الائتمان أولا، حيث كانت ضعيفة.
I hit income, that was a question mark.
وعند الوصول إلى قيمة الدخل وجدتها مجهولة.
I didn't know it was unknown, what do we do next?
بل لم أكن أعلم أنها مجهولة، فما الحل؟
So where a learning problem,
لذلك عند مصادفة مشاكل التعلم،
where you have some training data we tried some features, fed some machinery model,
في بعض بيانات التدريب حاولنا بعض الميزات، وقمنا بتغذية بعض نماذج الآلات،
which then use a quality metric to learn a decision tree T of x.
التي تستخدم بعد ذلك مقياس الجودة لتعلم تسلسل اتخاذ القرار T للمتغير x.
But, we're in a setting, where some of the data, might be missing a training time.
ولكننا في وضع، حيث قد تفقد بعض البيانات وقتًا للتدريب.
And, some of the data might be missing a prediction time.
وقد تفقد بعض البيانات وقتًا للتنبؤ.
And what do we do?
فما الحل؟
What we're going to do is modify the machinery model a little bit, the decision
ما سنفعله هو تعديل نموذج الآلة قليلاً،
tree model a little bit, to be able to deal with this kind of missing data.
وبالتحديد نموذج اتخاذ القرار، لتكون قادرة على التعامل مع هذا النوع من البيانات المفقودة.
Let's see how.
دعنا نري كيف نفعل هذا.
[MUSIC]
[موسيقى]